Walter B. Goad Papers 1942-2000 Mss.Ms.Coll.114
American Philosophical Society
- Series III. GenBank
  Materials relating to the founding and first ten years of operation of GenBank, including general correspondence, correspondence with Bolt, Baranek and Newman (contractors for the database and networking operations), contracts with government agencies, and grant proposals.
  As a member of the GenBank Advisory Group, Goad took part in meetings concerning the structuring of the database, its relationships with similar enterprises in the United States, Europe and Japan, and in reporting on its development. Along with selected minutes of the Advisory Group, the series includes memos and other documents submitted to Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory to document GenBank-related activities, information on "competitors" and peers (e.g. Genet, MolGen, PROPHET, and Japanese nucleic acid data banks), studies of computing needs and facilities for GenBank, and users' manuals for submitting data to GenBank and using the database. Materials filed under EMBL consist primarily of correspondence and documents relating to meetings with EMBL and documents presented to Los Alamos to support requests for reimbursement.
  The "Los Alamos Internal documents" include Goad's status reports to the Lab and his prospectuses for research and funding submitted to supervisors. These provide an important perspective on the internal support at Los Alamos for the development of GenBank and Among the more interesting manuscripts in the series are "Computer Storage and Analysis of DNA Sequences," 1982 (a status report to the Institutional Supporting Research and Development); "DNA as Molecular Processor," ca.1984 (proposal); "Identification of Functional Similarities in Nucleic Acid Sequences," 1984 (draft proposal), and a draft of Jim Fickett's "five year plan" for the redesign of GenBank, 1987. A printout of a program in FORTRAN for detecting homologous sequences, 1984, is a relic of an earlier era of programming.
  - Correspondence 1, 1979-1980; GenBank (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 2, 1981-1982; GenBank (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 3, 1983; GenBank (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 4, 1984; GenBank (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 5, 1985-1986; GenBank (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 6, 1987; GenBank (Box 3)
  - Correspondence with Bolt, Beranek, and Newman 1, 1981-1982; GenBank (Box 3)
    Includes business proposal and amendments; BBN proposal to NIH
  - Correspondence with Bolt, Beranek, and Newman 2, 1982; GenBank (Box 3)
    Reponses to questions from NIH regarding proposal of 1982
  - Correspondence with Bolt, Beranek, and Newman 3, 1983; GenBank (Box 3)
    Proposal to NIH to support data management, data collection and distribution for GenBank
  - Correspondence with Bolt, Beranek, and Newman 4, 1984-1987; GenBank (Box 3)
    Includes grant proposal to Dept. of Agriculture for maintenance of plant genetic sequences
  - Contracts 1, 1981-1982; GenBank (Box 3)
    Contracts with NIH, Intelligenetics
  - Contracts 2, 1980-1987; GenBank (Box 3)
    Supporting information for contracts, including correspondence and agreements, resumes for investigators; verification of trademark on "GenBank"
  - Proposals, 1981-1987; 3 items; GenBank (Box 3)
    Proposed addendum to R01-GM2706, 1981; "Center for Computer Analysis of Macromolecules,"
  - Correspondence, 1982-1983; GenBank. Advisory Group (Box 4)
    Notes and correspondence regarding Advisory Group.
  - Minutes and notes 1, 1984; GenBank. Advisory Group (Box 4)
  - Minutes and notes 2, 1985; GenBank. Advisory Group (Box 4)
  - Minutes and notes 3, 1986; GenBank. Advisory Group (Box 4)
  - Minutes and notes 4, 1987; GenBank. Advisory Group (Box 4)
  - Competitors, 1980-1989; 7 folders; GenBank--Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    Materials relating to other nucleic acid databases, either "competitors" or colleagues of GenBank
    - Genet, 1982 (Folder 1)
    - Japanese databases, 1982-1986 (Folder 2)
    - Molecular Biology Computer Research Resource, 1986 (Folder 3)
      Includes application for grant from Dana-Farber Cancer Institute to USPHS for Molecular Biology Computer Research Resource
    - MolGen, 1980-1981 (Folder 4)
      Includes "An Introduction for guests pf MOLGEN on SUMEX-AIM," 1980 and 1981; minutes of workshop on need for a nucleic acid sequence database, 1980; and proposal to NSF for funding MOLGEN, 1983
    - National Biomedical Research Foundation, 1980-1982 (Folder 5)
      Re: Margaret Dayhoff's system
    - PROPHET, 1982 (Folder 6)
    - Protein Databank, 1987-1989 (Folder 7)
      Protein Databank Newsletters no. 40-47
  - Computing materials, 1979-1987; 3 folders; GenBank--Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Applications of Supercomputers in Life Sciences, 1984-1986 (Folder 1)
      Materials on Workshop on the Applications of Supercomputers in Life Sciences (1984), including the proceedings, and NSF Office of Advanced Scientific Computing
    - ESNet, 1986-1987 (Folder 2)
      Materials relating to the Energy Sciences Network, including Five Year Networking Plan (1987), minutes, notes and correspondence for Steering Committee; planning and status documents relating to the internet and HEPNET (High Energy Physics Comp. Net.)
    - Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory--T-10 Computer use, 1979-1983 (Folder 3)
      Re: computer use in Division T-10 at Los Alamos
  - GenBank: The First 15 Years., Contains material relating to the Symposium Honoring Dr. Walter Goad.
    - "Hello Walter.", n. d.; 1.0 Item(s); Two photographs, a crowd in each holding letters that spell "Hello" and "Walter" respectively.
  - Database design notes, 1983-1984; GenBank--Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Homology program (FORTRAN), 1984; GenBank--Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - EMBL materials 1, 1979-1982; GenBank--Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    Correspondence, agendas, etc. re: workshops and meetings, including "Computing and DNA Sequences" workshop, 1980; proposal for Intl. Workshop on Nucleotide Sequence Databases, 1982; recommendations on Nucleotide Sequence Data Library, 1982; travel reports
  - EMBL materials 2, 1983-1987; GenBank--Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    Includes computer printout of letter from Hamm and Goad regarding LASL/GenBank/EMBL cooperation; notes on EMBL workshop on "Future of the Biocomputing Programme," 1985, including final report
  - Los Alamos internal documents, 1981-1989; 3 folders; GenBank--Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Los Alamos internal documents 1, 1981-1985 (Folder 1)
    - Los Alamos internal documents 2, 1986-1987 (Folder 2)
    - Los Alamos internal documents 3, 1988 (Folder 3)
      Includes research report by Daniel B. Davidson, 1988; proposals and summaries of activity
  - Manuals, 1982-1984; GenBank--Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    Manuals or guides for access and participation in Los Alamos Nucleic Acid Sequence Data Bank, including "Los Alamos Nucleic Acid Sequence Data Bank and Computer Analysis Center"
  - Reference materials, 1976-1981; GenBank--Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    Miscellaneous materials relating to database query and design
  - "Science article", 1986; GenBank--Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    Drafts of Bilofsky et al., "Data banks of nucleic acid sequence: GenBank" and Burks et al. "GenBank: The Genetic Sequence Data Bank" (the latter published in Science)
  - Submissions forms for data, ca.1985?; GenBank--Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Viewgraphs, 1986-1988; GenBank--Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    Overhead transparencies for presentations on GenBank
  - Miscellaneous materials 1, 1979-1982; GenBank--Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    Includes data on E. coli, M1 RNA homology search
  - Miscellaneous materials 2, 1983-1984; GenBank--Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    Includes copy of TMs "Nucleotide Sequence Data Banks"
  - Miscellaneous materials 3, 1985-1986; GenBank--Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    Includes flow charts for data and resource management, misc. materials relating to grants; TMs "Redesigning GenBank: An Overview" by Jim Fickett (a "five-year plan")
  - Miscellaneous materials 4, 1987-1991; GenBank--Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    Includes 1987 status report on GenBank, notes on PCR (ca.1990) and DNA denaturation
- Series IV. Human Genome Project
  Materials relating primarily to the planning stages for the Human Genome Project, many emanating from Goad's participation in the Advisory Panel. Goad attended several early planing workshops in which the sequencing and analytical technologies were fleshed out, with the intention of tapping newer technologies to scale up the mapping and sequencing enterprise, including polymerase chain reaction and the intensive use of computers and robotic approaches. In addition to a small suite of materials from the Human Genome Management Plan workshop, the final report from the Human Genome Workshop held in Santa Fe, 1986, provides a good technological and conceptual baseline for the project.
  - Human Genome Project 1, 1986 (Box 7)
    Some correspondence, planning documents, and miscellany relating to Human Genome Project; respecting planning and methodology for the project
  - Human Genome Project 2, 1987 (Box 7)
    Includes statement of operations of Human Genome Project, 1987; published "Report on the Human Genome Initiative," April 1987; and Articles of Incorporation of the Human Genome
  - Human Genome Project--Grant proposals, 1986 (Box 7)
    Includes applications and related material to DOE for "Computational Analysis..," "Technical and Eonomic Analysis of Biomass Technologies," "Human Genome: Chromosome-specific Physical Mapping," "Enhancing Genomic DNA Analysis with Robotic Automation"
  - Human Genome Project--Publications 1, 1986 (Box 7)
    Includes semi-published(?) position paper on major issues facing the Project by harles Cantor; "DOE Human Genomic Technical Tool Development Program Recommendations" by Temple Smith; "Human Genome Initiative Proposal for Discussion by the HERAC DOE Subcommittee"
  - Human Genome Project--Publications 2, 1988 (Box 7)
    Publications, drafts, and notes on Sirotkin and Loehr, "The Interface Between Computational Science and Nucleic Acid Sequencing"; Moyzis et al., "The Distribution of Interspeed Repetitive DNA Sequences..."; and Sirotkin et al. "Computer Simulation..."
  - Human Genome Project--Publications 3, 1988 (Box 7)
    Drafts and assorted materials relating to Goad et al., "Multiplex Walking: A Proposal"
  - Human Genome Project--OTA 1, 1986-1987 (Box 7)
    Materials relating to Mapping the Human Genome Advisory Panel Meeting, 1987, including proposal for an OTA assessment and an OTA preliminary memo on "Status of Mapping and Sequencing" of project
  - Human Genome Project--OTA 2, 1987 (Box 7)
    Drafts of chapters 2-7 of OTA report
  - Human Genome Project--Site visits, 1986-1993 (Box 8)
    Material re: site visits to Laboratory of Mathematical Biology, National Cancer Institute
  - Human Genome Project--Workshops (Santa Fe, 1986) 1, 1985 (Box 8)
    Final report packet from Human Genome Workshop (Santa Cruz, Calif., 1985), including list of participants; "Program for Large-Scale Analysis of Nucleotide Sequences" (Anderson and Anderson); agenda; "Technology" (Comings); "Memo" (Gilbert); "Cost of Sequencing" (Burks); memo for Howard Hughes Medical Inst.
  - Human Genome Project--Workshops (Santa Fe, 1986) 2 (Box 8)
    Comments from participants in Human Genome Workshop (Santa Fe, N.M., 1986), included with final report. Also: "Models of the enterprise" and draft and email from Goad to Mark Bitensky of his thoughts on the Human Genome Project; including David C. Ward, "Summary Statement of DNA Sequencing Technology." Also: "non-technical document" relating to sequencing the
  - Human Genome Project--Workshops (Santa Cruz, 1985) (Box 8)
    "Notes and conclusions from the Human Genome Workshop"
  - Human Genome Project--Workshops (Denver, 1987) (Box 8)
    Documents from Human Genome Management Plan workshop, including description of Howard Hughes Med. Inst. participation, American Type Culture Collection (re: repository of DNA probes); Jett et al. "A Method for Rapid Base Sequencing in DNA"; DOE grant applications for Human Recombinant DNA Library and "Human Genome Sequencing: Robotic Vision"; Chuck Watson on data management; "Advanced Concepts for Base Sequencing in DNA"
- Series V. Conferences and workshops
  Information on a variety of molecular biological and data analysis conferences and workshops in which Goad participated. The most voluminous files are those from the CODATA conferences and Numerical Data Advisory Board of the NRC, but there is information on the NIGMS Nucleic Acid Sequence Data Bank Workshop (1980); the Aspen Center conference of the Acquisition, Integration, and Analysis of Molecular Genetic Information (1982); the NSF Advisory Committee on Advanced Computing (1983-1984); the Hayashibara Forum (Okayama, Japan, 1987); the Complex Carbohydrate Structure Data Base Workshop (1986); the workshop "Exploring the Role of Robotics and Automation in Decoding the Human Genome" (1987); and the Workshop on Algorithms for Molecular Genetics (1988). The series includes two interesting typescripts: "Data Management for Physical Mapping" and "Notes on the Lehrach Probe Hybridization Map" by G. P. Smith, both from 1987.
  - Acquisition, Integration, and Analysis of Molecular Genetic Information... (Aspen Center for Physics, 1982) (Box 9)
    Information from Workshop on Computational Analysis of DNA Sequences held at Aspen Center for Physics, August-Sept., 1982, including "Terminal Progress Report"
  - Baca Conference, 1981 (Box 9)
    Schedule for conference
  - Committee on Biotechnology Nomenclature and Information Organization, 1986 (Box 9)
  - Hayashibara Forum, 1987 (Box 9)
    Workshop in Okayama, Japan,organized by Akiyoshi Wada, including abstracts of papers presented, offprints, list of participants.
  - CODATA 1, 1984 (Box 9)
    Material relating to CODATA and Numerical Data Advisory Board, including report of the Education Panel of the Numerical Data Advisory Board.
  - CODATA 2, 1985-1986 (Box 9)
    Material relating to CODATA and Numerical Data Advisory Board.
  - CODATA 3, 1987 (Box 9)
    Documents and correspondence relating to 1st CODATA Workshop (Gaithersburg, 1987), including minutes of steering committee (Goad was a member).
  - CODATA 4, 1984-1985; 4 items (Box 9)
    Mintues of Meetings of the Numerical Data Advisory Board, U.S. National Committee for CODATA (July 23, 1984, Jan. 29, 1985; July 11, 1985).
  - Marine Biological Laboratory (Woods Hole, Mass.), 1988 (Box 9)
    Materials for participants in Molecular Evolution course at MBL, including list of participant, schedule, list of participants, and overhead transparencies. Photo of participants transferred to Series VI: Photographs.
  - National Library of Medicine, 1988 (Box 9)
    Materials for Workshop on Algorithms for Molecular Genetics
  - National Institute of General Medical Sciences, 1980 (Box 9)
    Nucleic Acid Sequence Data Bank Workshop (1980: Bethesda, Md.), including agenda, notes, and Goad's "Summary and observations"
  - National Institute of Health, 1987; 3 items (Box 9)
    Minutes of Working Group (Los Alamos) for July 14 and August 11, 1987.
  - National Science Foundation, 1983-1984 (Box 9)
    Materials relating to Advisory Committee on Advanced Computing, including draft proposal for USERNET participation.
  - United States. Department of Energy 1, 1986 (Box 9)
    Materials relating to the Complex Carbohydrate Structure Data Base Workshop (1987: Auburn, N.Y.), including list of participants, summary.
  - United States. Department of Energy 2, 1987 (Box 9)
    Materials relating to workshop: Exploring the Role of Robotics and Automation in Decoding the Human Genome, including agenda, list of participants, report
  - United States. Department of Energy 3, 1987 (Box 9)
    Materials relating to workshop on physical mapping of genome, including draft TMs on "Data Management for Physical Mapping" and "Notes on the Lehrach Probe Hybridization Map" by G. P. Smith.
  - Miscellaneous, 1984-1987 (Box 9)
    Miscellaneous materials relating to various conferences and symposia, including the Symposium on the Analysis of Genetic Squences and the Symposium on Biological Applications on Cray
- Series VI. Biographical and personal
  Miscellaneous materials of a biographical, autobiographical, or personal nature, including Goad's diplomas, certificates of fellowship in scientific societies, his military service records, and articles about Goad and his research that appeared in the New York Times Magazine, Science, Omni, the Los Alamos Newsbulletin, and local newspapers. The series contains two two-page autobiographical pieces written by Goad, and a longer, though incomplete memoir, written ca.2000.
  - Articles about Goad--Los Alamos Bulletin, 1982-1987; 8 items (Box 11)
    Articles mentioning Goad extracted from the Los Alamos National Laboratory Newsbulletin
  - Articles about Goad--Miscellaneous, 1980-2001; 12 items (Box 11)
    Articles mentioning Goad from various publications, including Science, Omni, NY Times
  - Curriculum vita, 1985-1988; 4 items (Box 11)
    Three versions of Goad's c.v.
  - Family materials, 1952-2000 (Box 11)
    Miscellaneous family-related material, including chronology of his life by his wife, Maxine Goad; Goad genealogy; annual family newsletters (1989-2000), selected correspondence with wife and children; wedding announcement, and article on Maxine Goad's career.
  - Grainger High School Yearbook, 1942 (Box 11)
    Yearbook, with signatures, from Goad's senior year in high school, Kinston, N.C.
  - Memoir (incomplete), 1994-2000; 3 items; Goad, Walter B., 1925-2000 (Box 11)
    Three autobiographical memoirs of Goad, all brief, the last incomplete.
  - Memorial gathering, 2000; 8 items (Box 11)
    Program for memorial gathering and statements by friends and colleagues read there.
  - Military service record, 1942-1954 (Box 11)
    Official records of Goad's service in the Navy and Naval Reserve.
  - Obituaries, 2000; 8 items (Box 11)
  - Organizations and Societies, 1945-1975; 5 items (Box 11)
    Membership certificates or notice of election to Fellowship in American Association for the Advancement of Science (1968) and American Physical Society (1975); Eleanor Roosevelt Inst. For Cancer Research (1974); and Sigma Xi (1945); appointment as Laboratory Fellow, Los Alamos (1987).
  - Union College Commencement Exercises (Program), 1945; 1 item (Box 11)
  - Diplomas, 1942-1954; 3 items (Box 11)
    High School Diploma (Grainger High School, Kinston, N.C., 1942), BS, Union College (1945), Ph.D., Duke (1954)
  - Los Alamos National Laboratory Certificate of Excellence, 1988; 1 item (Box 11)
  - GenBank: The First 15 Years. A Symposium Honoring Dr. Walter Goad, 1991; Scrapbook (Box 11)
- Series VII. Miscellaneous and photographs
  Miscellaneous manuscript materials and candid and studio photographs of Goad, his family, and colleagues. The manuscripts contain an interesting series of drafts from the Executive Committee of the Los Alamos Branch of the Federation of American Scientists (FAS), March 1955, objecting to the tone of a statement issued by the national FAS of hydrogen bomb testing, and a typescript "Comments on FAS Release of H-Bomb Test Dangers." Also included are a bound laboratory notebook and miscellaneous notes from Goad's research in bioinformatics,
  - H-bomb memoranda, 1955 (Box 12)
    Responses to Federation of American Scientists statement on the H-bomb from the Los Alamos Chapter of the FAS, including draft to the Executive Committee of the Los Alamos Chapter objecting to the tone of the statement; a memorandum to the Executive Committee of the Los Alamos Chapter; a draft of a statement from the Los Alamos Chapter, and "Comments on FAS Release of H-Bomb Test Dangers;" misc. drafts
  - Laboratory notebook, 1972-1979; 1 vol.; Goad, Walter B., 1925-2000 (Box 12)
  - Laboratory notes, n.d.; Goad, Walter B., 1925-2000 (Box 12)
  - Walter B. Goad at Los Alamos, 1982-1987; 7 photoprints (Box 12)
    Formal and informal portraits of Goad, including:
    1) With model of DNA (for awarding contract toGenBank), 1985
    2) Goad and Jim Fickett, 1982
    3) Goad and unidentified female colleague, 1982
    4) Goad, Christian Burks, et al. and Los Alamos, 1984
    5) Goad at blackboard, Los Alamos, 1984
    6) Goad at computer, 1984
    7) Goad in his office at Los Alamos, 1987
  - Walter B. Goad portraits, 1945-2000; 17 photoprints (Box 12)
    Miscellaneous photos of Goad:, including:
    1) Goad as naval officer, 1945
    2) Goad and Maxine Steineke Goad upon engagement, August 1952
    3) Goad and Maxine Goad in the garden of their home in El Rancho, N.M., April 1998 (color)
    4, 5) Goad at home in El Rancho, N.M., fall 1979 (two photos, color)
    6) Studio portrait, ca.1980
    7) Goad and three colleagues at Eleanor Roosevelt Inst. Genetic Symposium, fall 1986
    8) Goad, Ted Puck, Leonard Lerman, and Arthur Robinson at Eleanor Roosevelt Inst. Genetic
    Symposium, fall 1986
    9, 10) Goad and Goad and Maxine Goad on rafting trip on Rio Grande, Tex., March 1987 (2
    photos, color)
    11) Goad on Folkboat, B.C. 1990 (color)
    12) Goad on Folkboat, Desolation Sound, B.C. May 1992 (color)
    13) Goad at anchor, Aristazabal Island, B.C., August 1996 (color)
    14-17) Goad on trip to Chilean Andes, March 2000 (4 photos, color)
  - Walter B. Goad family, 1972-1998; 13 photoprints (Box 12)
    Candid photos of Goad, his wife, children, and grandchildren, most in color
  - Los Alamos, 25 Years Service Awards, 1976; 1 photoprint (Box 12)
    Group portrait of recipient of 25 Years Service Awards, Los Alamos, January 22, 1976
  - Molecular Evolution Course, Woods Hole, 1988; 1 photoprint (Box 12)
    Group portrait of participants in Molecular Evolution Course held at Woods Hole, 1988
  - Goad's Travels: The Gulf of California Under Sail, 1968; 1 vol. (27p. and 9 photoprints) (Box 12)
    Diary of family sailing outing to Gulf of California, 1968
  - Goad's Travels: British Columbia Under Sail, 1993, 1995; 2 vols. (4 photoprints) (Box 12)
    Maxine Goad's diaries of sailing vacations in British Columbia
  - Photos for publication, ca.1982-1985; 34 photoprints (Box 12)
    Miscellaneous photos of figures from published works
  - Miscellaneous overhead transparencies, ca.1982-1985 (Box 12)
    Miscellaneous transparencies and other materials used in presentations regarding GenBank and nucleic acid databases and analysis
  - Posters, 1991, 1994; 2 items (Box OS)
    Poster for Symposium Honoring Walter Goad (NIGMS, 1991), and for Theoretical and Computational Biology Workshop (1994)